

# **Curriculum Vitae for Trygve Bærland**

#### Personal information

Address: Fagerliveien 1 E-mail: trygve@xal.no

0587, Oslo Phone: (+47)93839327

Born: 11.09.1991

### **Summary**

Holds a civil engineering degree in industrial mathematics from NTNU, and a Ph.D. at the department of mathematics, University of Oslo. Excellent analytical skills with a strong foundation in mathematics and physics. Has written computational code extensively throughout work in industry and research.

#### **Technical skills**

Languages Python, C and C++, Fortran, Matlab

Tools Git, Linux, Docker, Confluence, Jira, LaTex, SWIG, Boost libraries,

FEniCS, MFEM, Pytest, Doctest, Sphinx

#### Education

2015 – 2019 Ph.D. in mathematics, University of Oslo. Preconditioners for discre-

tizations of multiphysics problems. The work included developing efficient solvers, proving mathematically their robustness, and developing numerical software to exhibit their efficacy. Research results were pub-

lished in scientific journals and presented at conferences.

2010 – 2015 Civil engineer in industrial mathematics from the norwegian university

of science and technology, NTNU. Master's thesis was on the analysis of spectral methods on anamolous diffusion equations. Many courses in physics, mathematics and computer science throughout the educa-

tion.

# **Professional experience**

| 2019 –      | Consultant, Expert Analytics   |
|-------------|--|
| 2015        | Maple T.A. in course on multi-variable calculus, NTNU. Creating  |
| 2014        | electronic exercises and guiding students in their course work.  Summer internship at Sintef MARINTEK, construction technique. |
| 2014        | Benchmarking numerous fast Fourier transform implementations in  |
|             | Fortran, C, and CUDA.  |
| 2014        | Lead teaching assistant in course on linear algebra, NTNU. Respons-  |
| 2014        | ible for guiding and helping the other teaching assistants in the course.  |
| 2012 – 2013 | Summer internships as pricing analyst for If skadeforsikring, liability  |
| 2012 2013   | insurance. Worked on, amongst other things, designing and implemen-  |
|             | ting new pricing models for corporate insurances.  |
| 2012 - 2013 | Film club manager for Studentersamfundets Filmklubb. The film club   |
| 2012 2010   | had weekly movie screenings throughout the school year. Responsibi-  |
|             | lities included acquiring screening rights, organizing events, as well as  |
|             | working with the treasurer on budget and accounting.   |
| 2011 - 2012 | Treasurer for the cultural committee at Studentersamfundet in Trond-   |
|             | heim. The cultural committee is responsible for organizing events du-  |
|             | ring weekdays at Studentersamfundet in Trondheim. The treasurer  |
|             | is responsible for working out yearly budgets and accounting for the   |
|             | committee. Responsibilities also included organizing cultural events   |
|             | like debates and lectures.   |
| 2011 – 2014 | Teaching assistant in various courses on mathematics at NTNU. In-  |
|             | troductory courses on analysis and calculus.   |
| 2010 – 2011 | Work during summers as home help for Drammen municipality.   |
|             |  |

## Languages

Norwegian Native speaker and writer English Speak and write fluently

### Some interests and hobbies

Technology programming, numerical software Personal sewing, tennis, playing music

# **Extended descriptions of selected projects**

Activity Short term production planning with Statkraft

 $\begin{array}{ll} \text{Period} & 08/2019\text{-}12/2020 \\ \text{Role} & \text{Backend developer} \end{array}$ 

Staffing 3-5 developers, 3-7 project owners, 1 project manager

Volume 50-100 %

Description Trygve worked with development of a tool for hydro power produc-

tion planning for Statkraft. Here he built a system for solving various optimization problems on demand from either Python scripts or web

applications.

Tools Python, C++, Angular, Apache

Activity Analysis platform development with Statkraft

Period 02/2018-12/2020

Role Developer Volume 50-100 %

Description Trygve worked with development, maintenance and surveillance on the

computer clusters used in many of Statkraft's analysis pipelines.

Tools Python, C++, Bokeh, Gitlab, systemd

Activity Forecasting models for balancing power markets with Cognite and

Hafslund Eco

 $\begin{array}{ll} \text{Period} & 01/2021\text{-}06/2021 \\ \text{Role} & \text{Data scientist} \end{array}$ 

Staffing 3 developers, 1 domain expert, 2 project owners and 1 project mana-

ger.

Volume 100 %

Description Trygve worked with the development of price forecasting models based

on machine learning for the intraday- and regulating power markets, whose function is to resolve imbalances between production and consumption in the power grid. The models were set in production on Cognite's cloud infrastructure, and a GUI was built for traders to view

the predictions in a context to help in their decision making.

Tools Python, scikit-learn, XGBoost, Cognite Data Fusion

#### **Publications**

Journal Computational Methods in Applied Mathematics

Date June 2017

Authors Trygve Bærland, Jeonghun J. Lee, Kent-Andre Mardal, Ragnar Wint-

her

Title Weakly Imposed Symmetry and Robust Preconditioners for Biot's

Consolidation Model

DOI https://doi.org/10.1515/cmam-2017-0016

Journal Astronomy & Astrophysics

Date October 2017

Authors D.S. Seljebotn, T. Bærland, H.K. Eriksen, K.-A. Mardal, I.K. Wehus Title Multi-resolution Bayesian CMB component separation through Wiener

filtering with pseudo-inverse preconditioner

DOI https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201732037

Journal SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing

Date April 2019

Authors Trygve Bærland, Miroslav Kuchta, Kent-Andre Mardal Title Multigrid Methods for Discrete Fractional Sobolev Spaces

DOI https://doi.org/10.1137/18M1191488

Journal Numerical Methods for Partial Differential Equations

Date July 2020

Authors Trygve Bærland, Miroslav Kuchta, Kent-Andre Mardal, Travis Thomp-

son

Title An observation on the uniform preconditioners for the mixed Darcy

problem

DOI https://doi.org/10.1002/num.22500